Department of Sociology Records UA125
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Sociology Records
circa 1972 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Anthropology
Department of Sociology
UA125
7.5 Linear Feet
16 Digital Object(s) 16 digital objects containing 225 files.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Department of Sociology, 2016-2017.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series: 2016 accessions and 2017 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of Sociology was officially established in 1945, with Dr. A. Warren Stearns' appointment as chairman of the new department. To address the problems created by World War II, the Department of Sociology was meant to serve the postwar political atmosphere on a global scale. Its creation, along with the Department of Government in 1946, caused an increase in applications, particularly from veterans. Since its founding, professors in the Department of Sociology have advocated for drug education and warned against underage drinking, among other social problems. Pawan Dhingra became the Chair of the Department of Sociology in 2012. The Department aims to provide students with analytical skills to examine social interactions and developments on a worldwide scale.
Scope and Contents
This series contains annual reports, course listings, course files (including the research and course files of Tufts Associate Professor James Ennis), film reels, notes, posters, and syllabi. Sociology and Anthropology course listings include more in-depth course descriptions than those included in the Bulletin. There is also a DVD remembering Sy Bellin, former professor at Tufts.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs; Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material
- 2016 accessions, 1972 -- 2008; UA125.001; 6.9 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Transferred by the Department of Sociology, 2016, accession 2016.112.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This series may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains syllabi and course files; departmental annual reports; the research and course files of James Ennis, a professor in the department from 1983 through 2010; and a DVD remembering Sy Bellin, former chair of the department.
  - Soc 180-192 syllabi; Sociology and Sociology-Anthropology annual reports, circa 1972 -- 1990; UA125.001.001; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 1)
  - Soc 01-119 syllabi; Sociology and Sociology-Anthropology annual reports, circa 1980 -- 1993; UA125.001.002; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 2)
  - Soc 101-149 syllabi, circa 1980 -- 2006; UA125.001.003; 0.6 Linear Feet Half of one record carton (Box 3)
  - James Ennis research and course files, circa 1983 -- 2007; UA125.001.004; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 4)
    20 years from date of creation.
  - James Ennis social movements research, circa 1983 -- 2005; UA125.001.005; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 5)
  - James Ennis research (film reels); Sy Bellin DVD; miscellaneous department syllabi and course files, circa 1981 -- 2008; UA125.001.006; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 6)
    Custodial History
    1983 course assignment from Anthropology 20 found in reading room added to this box on December 13, 2017.
  - James Ennis social movements posters, circa 1978 -- 1990; UA125.001.007; .3 Linear Feet 1 oversize flat file (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 10)
- 2017 accessions, 1981 -- 2014; UA125.002; 0.6 Linear Feet Half of one record carton; 16 Digital Object(s) 16 digital objects containing 225 files.
  Transferred by the Department of Sociology, 2017, accession UA-2018-011.
  University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research.
  This series contains course files and syllabi from various professors in the department from the 1980s through the mid 2010s.
  - Course files and syllabi, circa 1981 -- 2014; UA125.002.003; 0.6 Linear Feet half of one record carton (Box 3)
  - Course Booklets: Fall 2003-Fall 2014, 2003 -- 2014; UA125.002.00001; 18 Digital Object(s); 29.5 Megabytes
    Open for research.
  - Spring 2008 Syllabi, UA125.002.00002; 4 Digital Object(s); 0.3 Megabytes
  - Fall 2008 Syllabi, UA125.002.00003; 7 Digital Object(s); 0.75 Megabytes
  - Spring 2009 Syllabi, UA125.002.00004; 6 Digital Object(s); 1.7 Megabytes
  - Summer 2009 Syllabi, UA125.002.00005; 1 Digital Object(s); 5.4 Megabytes
  - Fall 2009 Syllabi, UA125.002.00006; 15 Digital Object(s); 5.2 Megabytes
  - Spring 2010 Syllabi, UA125.002.00007; 15 Digital Object(s); 1.2 Megabytes
  - Fall 2010 Syllabi, UA125.002.00008; 16 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes
  - Spring 2011 Syllabi, UA125.002.00009; 11 Digital Object(s); 2 Megabytes
  - Fall 2011 Syllabi, UA125.002.00010; 16 Digital Object(s); 13.7 Megabytes
  - Spring 2012 Syllabi, UA125.002.00011; 21 Digital Object(s); 6.8 Megabytes
  - Fall 2012 Syllabi, UA125.002.00012; 17 Digital Object(s); 7.1 Megabytes
  - Spring 2013 Syllabi, UA125.002.00013; 20 Digital Object(s); 5.9 Megabytes
  - Fall 2013 Syllabi, UA125.002.00014; 17 Digital Object(s); 3.1 Megabytes
  - Spring 2014 Syllabi, UA125.002.00015; 19 Digital Object(s); 14.8 Megabytes
  - Fall 2014 Syllabi, UA125.002.00016; 22 Digital Object(s); 7.6 Megabytes